vomit-inducing talk of all time. I'm about to show you things that I think you'll find hard to unsee, but all in the name of science. First, for those unfamiliar with what I do, I guess if you distilled it right down to its essence, you would call me a beatboxer. (Beatboxing) Yo, for example ... here's a sample: (Beatboxing) (Rhythm changes) (Hums a tune) (Applause and cheers) Thank you. (Applause) And being a beatboxer, it means that professionally, I am 100 percent reliant on the -- (Beatboxing) flexibility of the unfiltered human voice. And for years, my contemporaries and I have been fielding questions like, "Oh my God, that's so cool. When did you figure out you could do that?" After I practiced for thousands and thousands of hours -- (Laughter) "And what do you do for a real job?" "I'm a full-time beatboxer, Your Honor." But there is one question that I get quite a lot that's a little bit more difficult to answer, and that is how are you doing it -- how are you making those noises? And I mean, I know muscle memory dictates where I position my lips in order to -- (Beatboxing) but I have no idea about the inner mechanics of everything. You know, all the flappy bits and kind of dangly things and how they interact in -- (Laughter) in a way that allows me to -- (Beatboxing) To put it metaphorically, I know how to drive, I just don't know what's under the hood. So I decided to find out and invite 5,000 captive strangers, a few uncomfortable cameras, everybody watching online and their browser history into a place where not even the most intimate of encounters have been ... my throat. And to help me do that, I'd like to introduce to the stage a very specialist guest from the Queensland Voice Center, a man that's been in my mouth more times than I'd care to admit, a legend of the larynx, ENT doctor and laryngeal surgeon,
et qui fait vomir de tout les temps. Je suis sur le point de vous montrer des chose que vous aurez du mal à oublier, mais tout ça au nom de la science. Avant tout, pour ceux qui ne connaissent pas ce que je fais, si vous creusez jusqu'à l'essence même, vous me définiriez comme un beatboxer (Beatbox) Yo, par exemple... voici un exemple : (Beatbox) (Changement de rythme) (Fredonne un air) (Applaudissements et acclamations) Merci. (Applaudissements) Et en étant un beatboxer, ça signifie que professionnellement, je dépends à 100 % de la -- (Beatbox) flexibilité de la voix humaine non filtrée. Pendant des années, mes contemporains et moi avons répondu à des questions comme « Oh mon Dieu, c'est magnifique. Quand as-tu compris que tu pouvais faire ça ? » Après m'être entraîné pendant des centaines et milliers d'heures... (Rires) « Et quel est ton vrai travail ? » « Beatboxer à plein temps, votre honneur. » Mais il y a une question qu'on me pose assez souvent et il est un peu plus compliqué d'y répondre, et c'est « comment tu le fais -- comment tu fais ces bruits ? » Eh bien, la mémoire musculaire me dit comment positionner mes lèvres pour -- (Beatbox) Mais je n'ai aucune idée du méchanisme profond des choses. Vous savez, tous ces trucs flasques et qui pendouillent et comment ils interagissent -- (Rires) de manière à me permettre -- (Beatbox) Pour employer une métaphore, je sais conduire, c'est juste que je ne sais pas ce qu'il y a en dessous du capot. J'ai donc décidé de le découvrir et d'inviter un public de 5 000 inconnus captifs, quelques caméras gênantes, tous ceux qui regardent en ligne et leur historique de navigation, dans un endroit où même les rencontres les plus intimes n'ont pas été... ma gorge. Et pour m'aider à faire ça, j'aimerais appeler sur scène un invité très spécialisé du Queensland Voice Center, un homme qui a été dans ma bouche plus de fois que je voudrais bien admettre une légende du larynx, ORL et chirurgien du larynx,
Matthew Broadhurst. (Applause and cheers) MB: Thank you, Tom, thank you. And a very good evening everyone. It is a pleasure to be here on the TEDx stage tonight. (Laughter) Whoo. TT: He's not warming up his hands. It doesn't get that intimate. MB: We set out a little while ago to try to go deep into the world -- and the throat -- of this beatboxer extraordinaire to try to understand how such a vast array of sounds are humanly possible. And what we found -- these are going in the mouth by the way -- and what we found was something absolutely amazing. Even after my two years of laryngeal surgery in Harvard Medical School with world-renowned professor Steven Zeitels, we never saw anything as extraordinary or fascinating as this,
Matthew Broadhurst. (Applaudissements et acclamations) MB : Merci, Tom, Merci. Et une très bonne soirée à tous. C'est un plaisir d'être sur la scène de TEDx ce soir. (Rires) Pfou ! TT : Il ne se chauffe pas les mains. Ce n'est pas si intime que ça. MB : Nous avons commencé il y a quelques temps à explorer le monde et la gorge -- de ce beatboxer extraordinaire pour comprendre comment une gamme si vaste de sons est humainement possible. Et ce qu'on a découvert -- ces gants vont dans la bouche -- et ce qu'on a découvert était absolument incroyable. Même après mes deux ans de chirurgie du larynx à la fac de médecine d'Harvard avec le professeur de renommée mondiale Steven Zeitels, nous n'avions vu rien de si extraordinaire ou fascinant
and that's what we're going to show you tonight. (Laughter) Alright, so for those of you who might be a little squeamish, the next 10 minutes or so will get incrementally more graphic and stomach-churning, so let's get into it -- TT: Feel free to use the bucket. (Laughter) MB: So when we make sound, we use the vocal cords to take air from the lungs and then turn it into a vibrating air column in the throat. If you think of it like a trumpet, we've got the mouthpiece -- that's the vocal folds -- and then the horn section is the throat. If we took your head off, took a bit of your neck off and left you as a torso with just your vocal folds vibrating, this is what you'd sound like. (Flatulent sound) TT: (High pitch) MB: Pretty hard to communicate, but fortunately we've got a throat. We've got all the soft tissues, and that actually gives you all the incredible dynamics of sound that you'll hear tonight. Now, this is a rigid laryngoscope. TT: Hmm, spicy boy. (Laughter) MB: I know, I know. 10 millimeters in diameter, it gives us the highest resolution image of the larynx we can get. And we teed up with a stroboscope here and a trigger microphone. The mic will pick up the frequency and that will allow us to show you how this all works. So, if we can have the lights down? TT: (Low pitch) MB: Turn the light on here. TT: (High and low pitches) MB: So I've got the frequency of sound matched with the stroboscope. That's the light you're seeing flickering in the cup. TT: (Low pitch) MB: And that's at about 80 hertz or so. So what we can do then is we can take that and put the phase of the strobe and the sound just out of sync. That lets us capture real-time, slow-motion activity of vibrating tissues. When we apply that to the larynx, we get this fluid, slow-motion of the vibrating vocal folds. So that's what we're going to get on and do. Alright, you ready? TT: Yup. (Laughter) MB: OK, so here we go. We're going to have a look at the voice box. (Laughter) It's very hard not to gag with this. Say, "e." TT: (Singing) E --
et c'est ce que nous vous montrerons ce soir. (Rires) Bien, donc pour ceux qui sont un peu sensibles, les prochaines 10 minutes environ seront de plus en plus graphiques et peuvent vous retourner l'estomac, alors allons-y. TT : le seau est là, au cas où. (Rires) MB : Donc lors de la production d'un son, nous utilisons les cordes vocales pour prendre de l'air des poumons pour le transformer ensuite en colonne d'air vibrant dans la gorge. En le comparant à une trompette, il y a l'embouchure -- donc les cordes vocales -- et le pavillon est la gorge. Si l'on retire la tête, si on enlève un peu de cou en laissant le buste seulement avec les cordes vocales qui vibrent, voici le son que vous produiriez. (Son de flatulence) TT : (Ton aigu) MB : Assez difficile pour communiquer, heureusement la gorge est là. Nous avons tous ces tissus mous, qui donnent en effet toute l'incroyable dynamique du son que vous écouterez ce soir. Maintenant, celui-ci est un laryngoscope rigide. TT : Hmm..t'es curieux. (Rires) MB : Je sais, je sais. 10 millimètres de diamètre, cela donne la plus haute résolution possible d'image du larynx. Nous l'avons attaché à un stroboscope ici et un microphone capteur. Ce micro captera les fréquences et cela nous permettra de vous montrer comment le tout fonctionne. Bien, peut-on éteindre les lumières ? TT : (Ton bas) MB : Allumez la lumière ici. TT : (Sons aigus et bas) MB : La fréquence du son est appairée au stroboscope. Il s'agit de la lumière clignotante que vous voyez dans le verre. TT : (Son bas) MB : Celui-ci est à environ 80 Hz. Nous pouvons aussi le prendre, et laisser la phase du strobe et du son hors syncro. Ainsi, nous pouvons capter en temps réel, et en ralenti l'activité des tissus vibrants. Quand on l'applique au larynx, nous obtenons une vibration fluide des cordes vocales vue au ralenti. Voila là où on arrivera et ce que l'on fera. D'accord, tu es prêt ? TT : Ouaip (Rires) MB : Ok, donc allons-y. Nous allons jeter un coup d'œil au larynx. (Rires) Tire la langue C'est vraiment difficile de ne pas s'étouffer. Dis « e ». TT : (Chantant) E --
MB: So down the bottom you see the vocal cords, the little cord-like structures. (Laughter) And now just look at the skin on the neck and you'll see how strong the light is to penetrate the skin. Alright, so if you'll have the lights back on? (Laughter)
MB: Tout en bas vous voyez les cordes vocales, comme des petites cordelettes. (Rires) Maintenant regardez la peau sur le cou et vous verrez que la puissance de la lumière pénètre la peau. Bien, on peut rallumer, s'il vous plaît ? (Rires)
(Applause) Alright, so just give us a comfortable "e." TT: (Singing) E. (Laughter) (Audience gasps) MB: So that's the vibrating vocal folds; about 120 hertz. Means they've collided 120 times a second just to make that sound. And we can also see that they're absolutely, perfectly normal. So all his beatboxing, all those sounds for years with Tom's way of doing it -- absolutely no damage whatsoever. That's really remarkable. Well done. OK. TT: (High pitch) We've got this. MB: So watch now as the vocal cords go from high pitch to low pitch. You'll see them go from long and skinny to short and fat. Really think "e." TT: (High to low pitch) E. MB: Right. MB: And what you can see is that his vocal range is so extreme -- much more extreme than any other performer I've worked with -- the machine actually can't capture the really high pitches. TT: (High pitch) MB: So we know that whistle register is somewhere around 2,092 hertz. That means the vocal cords, well over 2,000 times a second, are banging together just to make that sound. That's really extraordinary. If you think about them, they're only 15 millimeters long,
(Applaudissements) Bien, fais-nous un beau « e ». TT : (Chantant) E. (Rires) (Exclamation du public) MB : Voici les cordes vocales en vibration : environ 120 Hertz. Elles se sont donc entrechoquées 120 fois par seconde rien que pour produire ce son. Et nous pouvons aussi voir qu'elles sont parfaitement normales. Le fait de beatboxer, de produire ces sons pendant des années comme Tom le fait -- n'a absolument pas causé de dégâts. Vraiment remarquable. Très bien. Ok. TT : (Son aigu) Le voilà. MB : Regardez comment les cordes vocales changent d'un aigü à un grave. Vous les verrez longues et minces puis courtes et épaisses. Pense à un « e ». TT : (Son aigü puis grave) E. MB : Voilà. MB : Vous remarquerez que sa gamme vocale est si extrême -- bien plus que tous les autres artistes avec qui j'ai travaillé -- la machine ne peut en fait pas capter les sons vraiment aigus. TT : ( Son aigu) MB : Mais nous savons que le sifflement s'obtient au alentour des 2 092 hertz. Cela signifie que les cordes vocales, bien au delà des 2000 fois par seconde, s'entrechoquent pour produire ce son. C'est vraiment extraordinaire. A bien réfléchir, elles ne font que 15 mm de long,
so that's barely the width of your thumb. That's incred -- (Laughter) That's amazing this organ can do such a thing. So now we're going to swap over to the flexible laryngoscope. This is a little more graphic. TT: He bought it at SEXPO. (Laughter) MB: That wasn't in the script. (Applause) TT: Secondhand. (Laughter) MB: Now, we've had to time this bit perfectly because of the requirement for local anesthetic. You've got to numb the nose, get the camera in. It doesn't help for producing a lot of the sounds, but it gives us a really cool view of what's happening. So hold onto the stomachs, and let's see what we can do.
c'est à peine la longueur de votre pouce. C'est incroya -- (Rires) C'est surprenant que cet organe puisse faire ça. Maintenant nous allons introduire le laryngoscope flexible. Celui-ci est plus graphique. TT : Il l'a acheté au SEXPO. (Rires) MB : Ça n'était pas prévu dans le script. (Applaudissements) TT : C'est d'occasion. (Rires) MB : Nous avons dû mesurer parfaitement ce passage pour exécuter l'anesthésie locale. Il faut endormir le nez, insérer la caméra. Ça ne permettra pas l'émission d'une partie des sons mais nous avons ainsi un bon aperçu de ce qu'il se passe. Alors accrochez-vous et voyons ce qu'on peut faire.
(Audience gasps) So we're going to the back of the nose. And there you can see the soft palate. A lot of the sounds we make from day to day, even the simple ones, are incredibly complex. The sound "kh" for example. It's the soft palate sealing up precisely against the back of the nose. So if you say it loudly five times, feel your own soft palate snapping against the back of the throat. Kh, kh, kh, kh, kh, kh. Alright, so this is what it looks like when Tom does it. TT: Kh, kh, kh, kh, kh. A cacophony of cackling kookaburras and cockatoos in Kakadu couldn't quite quit ketamine. (Laughter) (Applause) MB: Alright, now in the beatboxing world, of course, they can use that for all sorts of different effects. I can help you. TT: This is fine, we're professionals. (Laughter) (Beatboxing) MB: Alright. (Applause and cheers) Now we're going to slide down a little further. If you'll just have the lights off and just see if you can see the light in the mouth somewhere. You'll be able to see exactly where the camera is at. (Laughter) TT: (Singing) Surprise. (Laughter) MB: Alright. (Audience gasps) So what you can see there, that's the base of the tongue. The side walls of the screen, that's the pharynx. All muscle walls, and in the deep, dark decks is the larynx. TT: Oh, should we have the lights back on? I think it's a good idea. It's getting a bit creepy with them off. MB: Turn the lights on, thanks.
(Exclamations du public) Maintenant nous allons au fond du nez. Et vous voyez ainsi le voile du palais. Beaucoup des sons qu'on produit chaque jour, même les plus simples, sont incoyablement complexes. Le son « kh » par exemple . C'est quand le voile du palais se colle exactement à l'arrière du nez. Si vous le dites fort cinq fois, vous sentirez votre voile du palais claquer contre le fond de la gorge. Kh, kh, kh, kh, kh, kh. Bien, voici à quoi ça ressemble quand Tom le fait. TT : Kh, kh, kh, kh, kh, kh. « A cacophony of cackling kookaburras et cockatoos à Kakadu couldn't quite quit ketamine ». (Rires) (Applaudissements) MB : Dans le monde de la Beatbox, ceci est utilisé pour toute sorte d'effets différents. Je peux t'aider. TT : Ça va, nous sommes professionnels. (Rire) (Beatbox) MB : D'accord. (Applaudissements et acclamations) Maintenant nous allons descendre encore un peu. Merci d'éteindre les lumières Prêtez attention à la lumière quelques part dans la bouche Vous pourrez voir exactement où la caméra se trouve. (Rires) TT : (En chantant) Surprise. (Rires) MB : Bien (Exclamation du public) Ce que vous voyez est la base de la langue. Sur les côtés de l'écran, c'est le pharynx. La paroie musculaire, et enfin, le canal sombre c'est le larynx. TT : Oh, nous devrions reallumer la lumière, non ? Oui, bonne idée. Ça fait un peu peur sans. MB : Lumière svp, merci.
Good. Now having examined over 15,000 larynxes and throats in my time, I can tell you that Tom's is as anatomically normal as anyone else's.
Bien. En ayant examiné 15 000 larynx et gorges dans ma carrière, je peux garantir que celle de Tom est anatomiquement normale
It's just his unique use of all the muscles and soft tissues which lets him do all these amazing sounds that you're going to hear. So we will dissect some of these sounds for you now. TT: It's in there really. Definitely. (Laughter) OK. (High-pitched sounds) (Hooting) MB: So what he's doing is he's changing the shape and the length of the vibrating air column using rhythmic contractions of all the muscles to generate all those sounds that you're hearing. (Beatboxing) (Laughter) (Low pitch) MB: And now there's rhythmic movements of the -- they're the arytenoid cartilages way down there, rocking back and forth to create that different sound. TT: (Low pitch) MB: And we like to call this "sphincter bass." (Laughter) And what you can see is that collapsing all the tissue down -- allows a different kind of really deep bass note. Alright, so with local anesthetic on board, a big black hose in the nose, we're going to let loose a sliver of his repertoire
C'est juste sa manière unique d'exploiter tous les muscles et tissus mous qui lui permet de faire tous ces sons magnifiques que vous écouterez. Nous allons décortiquer certains d'entre eux. TT : Je vous jure qu'il est là. Absolument. (Rires) Ok. (Sons aigus) (Hululement) MB : Ce qu'il fait, il change la forme et la longueur de la colonne d'air en vibration en exploitant les contractions rythmiques des muscles pour générer tous les sons que vous écoutez. (Beatbox) (Rires) (Sons graves) MB : et maintenant les mouvements rythmiques -- ce sont les cartilages aryténoïdes, qui font un va-et-vient pour créer ces différents sons. TT : (Sons graves) MB : On appelle ça la basse du sphincter. (Rires) Vous voyez qu'en abaissant tous les tissus -- il donne vie à des notes de basse très graves. Bien, avec l'anesthésie locale en cours, un gros tuyau noir dans le nez, nous écouterons un peu de son repertoire
and see all this in play. And we'll move -- careful. TT: Can you pull it up just a smidgeon. (Laughter) TT: (Beatboxing) Maybe just a little more -- (Laughter) Alright, cool, I think we're good. (Beatboxing) To all my peeps who came to get deep, deep as the abyss -- check this. (Beatboxing) (Cheers) (Applause) (Beatboxing) We start from the basics and build from scratch.
et nous verrons tout en direct. Nous allons bouger -- attention. TT : Tu peux le remonter juste un petit peu. (Rires) TT: (Beatbox) Peut-être encore un peu -- (Rires) D'accord, bien, c'est bon je pense. (Beatbox) Tout mes piaulements qui sont profonds, aussi profond que les abysses -- check this. (Beatbox) (Acclamations) (Applaudissements) (Beatbox) On commence par les bases pour construite une séquence.
(Record scratch) Yeah, like that. (Beatboxing)
(scratching) Oui, parfait. (Beatbox)
(Trumpet sound) (Beatboxing) Back to basics. (Beatboxing) (Beatboxing) You know the sound. (Beatboxing) Make some noise. (Applause and cheers) (Whistling) TT: Thank you so much.
(son de trompette) (Beatbox) Revenons aux bases. (Beatbox) (Beatbox) Vous connaissez le son. (Beatbox) Faites un peu de bruit. (Applaudissements et acclamations) (Sifflements) TT : Merci beaucoup.